David Watson

Pittsburgh, PA & (412) 614-9301 @ david@davidwatson.org

Summary

My work turns formless ideas into solid technology products.

By making sense of prototypes together, we arrive at user interfaces that transcend geometry. We grow teams to make better products. Conflict to consensus is sensemaking - a care and feeding of teams as a wormhole from code to culture.

Leadership is striving daily to be a good peer regardless of role, where teams scale better in pairs to meet platform demands using disposable scaffolding, immutable infrastructure, and well-defined ops. The best leader is the best peer.

Shipping data products and software services indicates readiness for funding, launch, and acquisition. Alleviating fears of diminishing returns and regressions by signifying product as production has value, but maintenance is production.

Trading user interface limits for user experience magic beyond data is gold.

Experience

Freelance (#) 2020-2024

- Carnegie Mellon University Senior Member of Technical Staff, ETC
- Caterpillar Technical Consultant (1099) GCC/C++/Linux Xilinx ZCU-104
- Wyvern Technical Consultant (1099) NodeJS, TypeScript, Docker, k8s

2018-2020

Software Engineering Specialist

Pittsburgh, PA

- Assembled Sensor Storage on Kubernetes using Python, Minio, and PostgreSQL with a team of 4 collaborators
- Built terrain visualization software in C++/gcc on Xilinx ZCU-104 using PYNQ with a team of 4 collaborators

Rent Jungle (RainMaker (RealPage)) @

2016-2018

Senior Software Engineer

Pittsburgh, PA

- Led weekly retro resulting in 2x better cadence, velocity, and teamwork
- · Crafted Scrapy crawler on Django, PostgreSQL, Kubernetes stack

Wellbridge Health @

2015-2016

VP Product Development

Pittsburgh, PA

- Led 4-person interdisciplinary design team through HIPAA-compliant EmberJS SPA MVP designed by MAYA delivered before remote health was common
- Developed REST API using Python/Django, <u>DRF</u> and PostgreSQL serving EmberJS SPA on Aptible with 4-person development team

Hire an Esquire (Major, Lindsey, and Africa) @

2014

VP Engineering

Pittsburgh, PA

- Led a team of 6 through a lean and agile redesign and refactoring of the entire UI/UX from legacy MVP Franken-Django system for attorneys and agents
- Reduced daily production firefighting by more than 50% using nimble methods, automated tests, CI/CD, and teachable moments during code review

Worldview

Linux

....

arch, debian, redhat, fedora, ubuntu

MacOS

• • • • 0

monterey, sequoia, BSD

Windows

• • • • •

11, WSL 2

Containers

Docker, Podman

• • • • 0

Virtualization

Heroku, VMWare

• • • • •

Private Cloud

Kubernetes, k3s, minikube

• • • • 0

k8s, helm

Public Cloud

AWS, GCP, Azure

• • 0 0 0

aws, gcp, azure

Databases

MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQLite

• • • • •

Frameworks (Scaffolding)

Django, Flask, Ruby on Rails

• • • • •

RoR

Programming Languages

C++

Microsoft VS Code and GCC

• • • • •

Markup

HTML, CSS, MarkDown (MD)

• • • • •

Python

OO, functional, OOA, OOD

• • • • 0

Ruby

Ruby on Rails (RoR)

• • • • •

Shell

bash, fish, zsh

• • 0 0 0

Experience (continued)

Forever @

2013-2014

Senior Software Developer

Pittsburgh, PA

- Prototyped the sketch our designer called, "flickr for dead people" in a couple weeks. Our founder said, "you hit the ball out-of-the-park".
- Enabled the company to move from 0 sales to strong market traction online via e-commerce platform completed working remote-hybrid with Neo, Columbus

SMaSh - Brainstorm SMS Technologies (Mind Matrix)



Senior Engineer

Pittsburgh, PA

- Wrote conversational text systems (like twilio) in Python/PostgreSQL
- Supported large SMS text campaigns from Pittsburgh Steelers to Miller-Coors

Wellspring Worldwide @

2010-2011

Software Development Manager

Pittsburgh, PA

- Pioneered SRE culture from legacy data center to SaaS VMWare CI/CD modernization with a team of 12 Engineers
- Built DevOps systems using Capistrano (Ruby), Mechanize (Python), and Selenium with dev team of 2 Sys Ops Engineers and 4 Test Ops Engineers

Applied Perception (Foster Miller (Qinetiq)) @

2008-2009

Project Engineer

Cranberry Township, PA

- Visualized XML sonar data in python, consumed by C++ GUI application on Windows
- Ported Microsoft C#.net Windows GUI to C++/Qt/Linux for OCU deployment

NOMOS (North American Scientific, Best Medical)

2006-2007

UI Software Engineer

Cranberry Township, PA

- Visualized XML sonar data in python with C++ GUI application on Windows
- Ported Microsoft C#.net Windows GUI to C++/Qt/Linux for OCU deployment

MAYA Design (BCG)

2004-2006

Software Design Engineer

Pittsburgh, PA

- Built python REST backends emitting JSON for consumption by AJAX frontends on dev team of 4
- Demoed GUI floorplan wireless lighting designer in C#.net on Windows for Lutron/Phillips 1 week from designer's sketch on interdisciplinary team

Cobind @

2003-2004

Founder

Pittsburgh, PA

- Collaborated on ideation, vision, and execution of custom Linux Tools startup with my cofounder and our PR consultant
- Received wide press acclaim around custom Linux products after winning Idea Foundry Fellowship and pairing with our PR consultant

Education

Duquesne University (4)

BS/BA

Business, Computer Science, Music

Awards

Top 100 Award

Infoworld

The MAYA Design team cobbled together parts predating AJAX, web components, and mapping APIs. They went on to found a...

- movement
- music school
- startup

as teams-of-pairs, coast-tocoast, taming complexity.

Transformation Fellowship Idea Foundry

Open Source is Social

My First FOSS Contribution

My Pull Request on Github

My Reactive Resume/Docker

My Github Profile

My LinkedIn Profile

Knowledge and Beliefs

Accelerate

Crystal Clear

Lean Software

Literate Programming

Peopleware

Realizing Empathy

Continuing Education

Git Foundations Workshop

RDBMS @ MIT

PyCon

References (redacted)

David Bishop

Lou Bojarski

Craig Maier

Bryan Mills

Tom Moertel

Elliott Williams